In this lesson,
we do a deep dive into evaluation.
We'll walk you through some
core concepts on how
to evaluate RAG systems. Specifically,
we
will introduce the RAG triad, a
triad of metrics for the three
main steps of a RAG's execution.
Context relevance, groundedness, and
answer relevance. These are
examples of an extensible framework of
feedback functions. Programmatic evaluations
of LLM apps. We then
show you how to
synthetically generate an evaluation
data set, given any
unstructured corpus. Let's get started.
Now I'll use a notebook
to walk you through the
RAG triad, answer relevance, context relevance,
and groundedness
to understand
how each can
be used with truelens to detect
hallucinations. At this
point, you
have already PIP
installed TruLens, eval and Llama Index.
So I'll not show you that
step. The first step for you
will be to set up an OpenAI
API key. The OpenAI key is used
for the completion step of the
RAG and to implement the evaluations
with TruLens. So
here's a code snippet
that does
exactly that. And you're now all set up
with the
OpenAI key. The next section, I will quickly recap
the query engine construction with Llama
Index. Jerry has
already walked you
through that
in lesson one in
some detail. We will
largely build on that lesson.
The first step now is to set
up a true object. From
TruLens eval, we are going to
import the true
class. Then we'll set up a true object
and instance of this class. And then
this object will be used to
reset the database. This database
will be used later on to
record the prompts, responses, intermediate
results of the Llama Index app,
as well as the
results of the various evaluations we will be
setting up with TrueLens.
Now let's set up
the Llama Index reader. So this
snippet of code reads this PDF document
from a directory on
how to build a
career in AI written
by Andrew Ang and then loads this data
into this document object.
The next step is
to merge all of this
content into a single large document rather than
having one document per
page, which is the
default setup. Next, we set up
the sentence index, leveraging some of
the Llama Index utilities. So you
can see here that we are
using OpenAI GPT 3.5 Turbo set at
a temperature of 0.1. As the
LLM that will be used for completion of the
RAG. The embedding model is set
to bge small, and version 1.5.
And all of this
content is being indexed with the sentence index
object. Next, we set
up the sentence window
engine. And this is the
query
engine that will be used later on
to do retrieval effectively
from this advanced RAG
application. Now that we
have set up the
query engine for sentence-window-based RAG,
let's see it in action
by actually asking a specific question.
How do you create
your AI portfolio? This will
return a full object with
the
final response from the LLM, the intermediate
pieces of retrieved context,
as well as some
additional metadata. Let's take a
look at what
the final response
looks like. So here you can
see the final response that came
out of this sentence window-based rag.
It provides a pretty good
answer on the surface to
this question of how do
you create your AI portfolio. Later
on, we will see
how to evaluate answers
of this form against
the RAG triad to build confidence
and identify failure modes for RAGs
of this form. for rags of
this form. Now that we have
an example of a response to
this question that looks quite good on
the surface, we will see how to make
use of feedback functions,
such as the rag
triad, to evaluate this kind of response more
deeply, identify failure modes, as
well as build confidence or
iterate to improve the
LLM application. Now that
we have set
up the sentence-window-based RAG
application, let's see how
we can evaluate it
with the RAG triad. We'll do a little
bit of housekeeping in the
beginning. First step is this,
is of course snippet that lets us
launch a StreamLit dashboard from
inside the notebook. You'll see
later that we'll make use of that
dashboard to see the results of
the evaluation and
to run experiments, to
look at different choices of apps, and to see
which to look at
different choices of apps
and to see which one
is doing better. Next up, we initialize
OpenAI GPT 3.5 Turbo
as the default provider
for our evaluations. And
this provider will be used to implement
the different feedback functions or evaluations, such
as context relevance, answer
relevance, and groundedness. Now,
let's go deeper into
each of the evaluations of the
RAG triad, and
we'll go
back and forth a
bit between slides and
the notebook to give you the full context.
First up, we'll discuss answer relevance.
Recall that answer relevance is checking
whether the final response
is relevant to the
query that was asked by the
user. To give
you a concrete example
of what the
output of answer
relevance might look
like, here's an example. The user
asked the question, how can altruism
be beneficial in building
a career? This was
the response that came
out of the RAG application.
And the answer
relevance evaluation produces two pieces
of output. One is
a score. On a scale
of 0 to 1, the
answer was assessed to be highly
relevant, so it
got a score
of 0.9. The second
piece is the supporting
evidence or the rationale or the chain
of thought reasoning behind
why the evaluation produced
this score. So here you can see that
supporting evidence found in the answer
itself, which indicates to the LLM
evaluation that it
is a meaningful
and relevant answer. I also
want to use this
opportunity to introduce the
abstraction of a feedback function.
Answer relevance is
a concrete example of a feedback
function. More generally, a feedback
function provides a score on a
scale of 0
to 1 after
reviewing an LLM
app's inputs, outputs,
and intermediate results. Let's now look
at the structure
of feedback functions using
the answer relevance feedback function as a concrete
example. The first component is a
provider. And in
this case, we can
see that we are using an
LLM from OpenAI
to implement these
feedback functions. Note
that feedback functions don't
have to be implemented necessarily using
LLMs. We can also use BERT models and
other kinds of mechanisms to implement feedback functions
that I'll talk about
in some more detail later
in the lesson. The
second component is that
leveraging that provider, we
will implement a feedback
function. In this case,
that's the relevance feedback function.
We give it a name,
a human-readable name that'll be shown
later in our evaluation
dashboard. And for this
particular feedback function, we run it
on the user input,
the user query, and it
also takes as input the final output
or response from
the app. So given
the user question and
the final answer
from the RAG,
this be by function will make use
of a LLM provider such as OpenAI
GPT 3.5 to come
up with a score for how
relevant the responses to
the question that was
asked. And in addition,
it'll also provide supporting evidence
or chain of thought reasoning
for the justification of that score.
Let's now switch back to the notebook and
look at the code
in some more detail. Now let's
see how to define
the question-answer relevance
feedback function in
code. From TruLens eval, we will
import the feedback class. Then
we set up the different
pieces of the question answer
relevance function that we were just
discussing. First
up, we have the provider, that is
OpenAI, GPT 3.5.
And we set up this particular
feedback function where the relevance score
will also be augmented with the
chain of thought
reasoning, much like
I showed in
the slides. We give this
feedback function a human-understandable
name. We call it answer relevance. This will be
show up later
in the dashboard,
making it easy for users to
understand what the feedback function is
setting
up. Then we also will give the
feedback function access to the input, that
is the
prompt, and the output, which
is the prompt, and the output, which is
the final response coming
out of the RAG application. With
this setup, later on in
the notebook, we will
see how to apply
this feedback function on
a set of records, get the evaluation
scores for answer relevance
as well as the chain of
thought reasons for why for that
particular answer that was the
judged score to be appropriate
for as part of
the evaluation The next
feedback function that we will go
deep into is
context relevance. Recall that context relevance
is checking how good the retrieval
process is. That is, given a
query, we will look at each
piece of retrieved context from the
vector database and
assess how relevant that piece of
context is to the question that
was asked. Let's look
at a simple example.
The question here or the prompt
from the user is, how can altruism
be beneficial in building
a career? These are
the two pieces of
retrieved context. And after
the evaluation with context
relevance, each of these pieces
of retrieved context gets a score
between 0 and 1. You
can see here the left
context got a relevant
score of 0.5. The right
score of 0.7, so
it was assessed
to be more relevant
to this particular query.
And then the mean
context relevant score is the average
of the relevant scores
of each of these
retrieved pieces of context. That gets
also reported out. Let's
now look at the structure of
the feedback function for
context relevance. Various pieces
of this structure are
similar to the structure for answer
relevance, which we reviewed a few
minutes ago. There is a provider,
that's OpenAI, and the
feedback function makes use of that
provider to implement the context-relevance feedback function. The
differences are in the
inputs to this particular
feedback function. In addition to the
user input or prompt,
we also share with this feedback function
a pointer to the retrieve contexts, that
is, the intermediate results
in the execution of
the RAG application. We get
back a score
for each of the retrieved pieces
of context, assessing
how relevant
or good that context
is with respect to
the query that was
asked, and then we
aggregate and average those scores
across all the retrieved pieces
of context to get the final
score. Now you will notice
that in the answer
relevance feedback function, we had
only made use of
the original input, the
prompt, and the final
response from the RAG.
In this feedback function,
we are making use
of the input or
prompt from the user,
as well as intermediate results, the set
of retrieve contexts, to assess the
quality of the retrieval. Between these
two examples, the full power
of feedback
functions is leveraged by making use of
inputs, outputs, and intermediate
results of a RAG application to
assess its quality. Now that we
have the context selection set
up, we are in a
position to define the context relevance feedback
function in code. You'll
see that it's pretty
much the code segment
that I walked through on the
slide. We are still using OpenAI
as the provider, GPT 3.5
as the evaluation LLM.
We are calling the question
statement or context relevance feedback function. It gets
the input prompt, the
set of retrieved pieces of context, it
runs the evaluation function
on each of those
retrieved pieces of context separately,
gets a score for
each of them, and then averages
them to report a final
aggregate score. Now,
one additional variant
that you can
also use,
if you like, is in
addition to reporting a context-relevant score for
each piece of retrieved context, you
can also augment it with chain-of-thought
reasoning so
that the evaluation LLM provides not only
a score, So that the
evaluation LLM provides not only a
score, but also a
justification or explanation for its assessment score.
And that can be done with QS
relevance with chain of
thought reasoning method. And
if I give you a concrete example
of this in action, you
can see here's the
question or the user
prompt, how can altruism be
beneficial in building a career?
This is an
example of a
retrieved piece of context
that takes out a
chunk from Andrew's article
on this topic. You
can see
the context relevance feedback function gives
a score of 0.7 on a
scale of 0 to
1 to this piece of retrieved context.
And because we have
also invoked the chain of
thought reasoning on the
evaluation LLM, it provides
this justification for why
the score is 0.7. Let
me now show you the
code snippet to set
up the groundedness feedback
function. We kick it off
in much the same way as the
previous feedback functions, leveraging LLM provider for
evaluation, which is, if you recall,
OpenAI GPT 3.5. Then we define
the groundedness feedback
function. This definition is structurally
very similar to the definition for context relevance. The
groundedness measure comes with chain of
thought reasons justifying
the scores, much
like I discussed on the slides. We give
it the name groundedness,
which is
easy to understand. And it
gets access to the set
of retrieved contexts in the RAG application,
much like for context
relevance, as well
as the final
output or response
from the RAG.
And then each
sentence in the final response gets
a grounded net
score, and those are aggregated, averaged, to
produce the final grounded net score
for the full response. The
context selection here is the same context selection
that was used for
setting up
the context relevance feedback function.
So if you recall, that
just gets the set of retrieved
pieces of context from
the retrieval step of
the RAG, and then can
access each node within that
list, recover the text of the
context from that node, and
proceed to work with that to
do the context
relevance as well as the groundedness
evaluation. With that,
we are now in a position
to start executing the
evaluation of the RAG
application. We have set
up all three feedback functions,
answer relevance, context relevance,
and groundedness. And all we
need is an evaluation
set on which we can
run the application and the evaluations and see
how they're doing and
if there are opportunities to
iterate and improve them further. Let's now look
at the workflow
to evaluate and
iterate to improve LLM applications. We will
start with the basic
Llama Index
RAG that
we introduced in the previous lesson
and which we have
already evaluated with the
TruLens RAG triad. We'll
focus a bit on the failure
modes related to the
context size. Then we
will iterate on that basic
rag with an advanced rag
technique, the Llama Index
sentence window rag. Next,
we will re-evaluate this new
advanced rag with the TruLens RAG
triad, focusing on these kinds of
questions. Do we see improvements specifically
in context relevance?
What about the other
metrics? The reason we focus on context relevance
is that often failure modes
arise because the context
is too small. Once
you increase the context up
to a certain point, you might
see improvements in context
relevance. In addition, when context
relevance goes up, often we
find improvements in groundedness as well.
Because the LLM in
the completion step has
enough relevant context to produce
the summary. When it does not
have enough relevant
context, it tends
to leverage its own internal knowledge
from the pre-training data set to
try to fill those gaps, which results in
a loss of groundedness.
Finally, we
will experiment with different window
sizes to figure out
what window size results
in the best evaluation metrics. Recall
that if the window size is
too small, there
may not be enough
relevant context to get
a good score on context relevance
and groundedness. If the window
size becomes too big,
on the other hand, irrelevant
context can creep into the final
response, resulting
in not such
great scores in
groundedness or answer relevance. We walked
through three examples of evaluations or
feedback functions. Context relevance, answer
relevance, and groundedness. In our
notebook, all three were
implemented with LLM evaluations.
I do want to
point out that feedback
functions
can be implemented in different ways. Often,
we see practitioners starting
out with ground truth
evals, which can be
expensive to collect, but nevertheless a
good starting point. We also
see people leverage humans to do
evaluations. That's also helpful
and meaningful,
but hard to scale
in practice. Ground truth evals, just
to give you a
concrete example, think of a summarization
use case where
there's a large
passage and then the
LLM produces a summary.
A human expert would then
give that summary a score indicating
how good it is. This can
be used for other
kinds of use cases as
well, such as chatbot-like use cases
or even classification use cases. Human
evals are similar
in some ways to ground truth evals
in that as the
LLM produces an output
or a RAG application produces
an output, the human users of
that application are going to
provide a rating for that
output, how good it is.
The difference with ground truth evals
is that these human users may
not be as much of an expert
in the topic as
the ones who produce
the curated ground truth
evals. It's nevertheless a
very meaningful evaluation. It'll
scale a bit better
than the ground truth
evals, but our degree of
confidence in it is lower. One
very interesting result from the research
literature is that if
you ask a set
of humans to rate
a question, there's about
80% agreement. And interestingly enough, when you use
LLMs for evaluation, the
agreement between the LLM
evaluation and the human evaluation
is also about
the 80 to 85%
mark. So that suggests that
LLM evaluations are quite comparable
to human evaluations for
the benchmark data sets to
which they have been
applied. So feedback functions
provide us a way to scale up evaluations
in a programmatic manner. In addition
to the LLM evals
that you have
seen, feedback functions also provide can
implement traditional NLP metrics
such as rouge scores
and blue scores. They
can be helpful in certain scenarios,
but one weakness
that they have
is that they
are quite syntactic.
They look for overlap between words
in two pieces of text.
So for example, if you have
one piece of text that's referring
to a river
bank and the other to
a financial bank, syntactically they
might be viewed
as similar, and
these references might
end up being viewed as similar
references by a traditional
NLP evaluation, whereas the
surrounding context will get
used to provide a
more meaningful evaluation when
you're using either large language
models such as GPT-4 or medium-sized
language models such
as BERT models, and to perform your evaluation.
While in the course we have given you
three examples of feedback functions
and evaluations, answer
relevance, context relevance, and
groundedness, TruLens provides a much broader
set of evaluations
to ensure that
the apps that you're
building are honest,
harmless, and helpful. These are all
available in the
open source library,
and we encourage you
to play with them as
you are working through the course
and building your LLM
applications. Now that we have
set up all the feedback functions,
we can set
up an object
to start recording,
which will
be used
to record
the execution of the application on
various records. So you'll see here
that we are
importing this Tru Llama class,
creating an
object, Tru Recorder of
this Tru Llama class. This
is our integration of
TruLens with Llama Index.
It takes in the
sentence-window-engine from Llama Index
that we had created
earlier, sets the app ID,
and makes use of the
three feedback functions of the RAG triad that
we created earlier. This
Tru recorder object will be used
in a little bit to
run the Llama Index application, as well
as the evaluation of these feedback
functions, and to
record it all in a local database.
Let us now load
some evaluation questions. In this
setup, the evaluation questions are set
up already in this
text file, and then we
just execute this code snippet to load them
in. Let's take a
quick look at these
questions that we will
use for evaluation. You
can see what are the keys to building
a career in AI, and
so on. And this
file you can edit
yourself and add your own
questions that you might want to get answers
from Andrew Ang. You
can also append
directly to the eval questions list
in this way. Now let's
take a look at the eval
questions list, and you can see that
this question has been
added at the end.
Go ahead and add your own
questions. And now we have everything
set up to get to the most
exciting step in this notebook with this
code snippet. We can
execute the sentence window
engine on each question
in the list of eval questions
that we just looked
at. And then with
Tru recorder, we are going to run
each record against the RAG triad. We will
record the prompts, responses, intermediate
results, and the evaluation
results in the true database.
And you can see here as the
execution of the steps
are happening for each
record, there is a
hash that's an identifier
for the record. As the
record gets added, we
have an indicator here
that that step has
executed effectively. In addition,
the feedback results for answer
relevance is done, and so
on for context relevance, and
so on. Now that we have
the recording done, we can
see the logs
in the notebook by
executing, by getting the
records and feedback and
executing this code snippet.
And I don't want
you to necessarily read
through all of the information
here. The main point I want
to make is that you can see the
depth of instrumentation and the application.
A lot of information
gets logged to the
tru recorder, and this
information are on prompts, responses, evaluation
results, and so
fault. And can be quite valuable to
identify failure mods in the
apps and to inform iteration
and improvement of the apps. All
of this information is valuable,
flexible JSON format, so they can be
exploded and consumed by
downstream processes. Next up,
let's look at some more human-readable format, for
prompts, responses, and the
feedback function evaluations. With
these quotes stampedes,
you can see that for
each input prompt or question,
we see the output and the
respective scores for
context relevance, groundedness, and answer relevance, and
this is run for
each and every entry
in this list of
questions and evaluations_questions.text. You can
see here the last question is
"How can I be successful in
the AI?" Was
the question that I
manually embedded to
that list have the end. Sometimes
in running the evaluations,
you
might see a non that
likely happen because of
API key failure. You just
want to rerun it to,
and show that the execution successfully
completes. I just
showed you a
record level view
of the evaluations, the prompts, responses, and evaluations,
let's now get an
aggregate view in the
leaderboard, which
aggregates across all of these individual records and
produces an average score across the 10 records
in that database. So
you can see here
in the leaderboard, the aggregate
view across all the 10
records. We had set
the app ID to
app 1. The average context
relevance is 0.56. Similarly, their average scores
for groundedness, answer
relevance, and latency
across all the 10 records of
questions that were asked of
the RAG application. It's
useful to get this aggregate view to
see how well your app
is performing and
at what level of latency and
cost. In addition
to the notebook interface, TrueLens also
provides a
local Streamlit app dashboard with which you can
examine the applications that
you're building, look at
the evaluation results, drill down into record-level views to
both get aggregate and detailed evaluation
views into
the performance of your app.
So we
can get the dashboard
going with the True.run
Dashboard method, and this
sets up a local database
at a certain URL.
Now once I click
on this, this might
show up in some
window, which is not within this frame.
Let's take a few minutes to
walk through this
dashboard. You can
see here the aggregate view of
the app's performance. 11 records
were processed
by the app and evaluated.
The average latency is
3.55 seconds. We have
the total cost, the
total number of tokens
that were processed by
the LLMs. And then scores
for the RAG triad. For
context relevance, it's
0.56. For groundedness, 0.86. And
answer relevant is 0.92. We can
select the app here to get
a more detailed record-evel view of the
evaluations. For each of the records, you
can see that the user
input, the prompt, the response,
this metadata, the timestamp, and
then scores for answer relevance,
context relevance,
and groundedness that have
been recorded, along with latency,
total number of tokens, and total cost.
Let me pick a row
in which the LLM indicates,
evaluation indicates that the LLM, the
RAG application has done well. Let's pick
this row. Once we click on a
row, we can scroll
down and get a more detailed
view of the different components of
that row from the table. So
the question here, the prompt
was, what is the first
step to becoming good at AI? The
final response from the
RAG was, is to
learn foundational technical skills. Down here,
you can
see that the
answer relevance was
viewed to be
one on a scale
of zero to 1. It's a relevant, quite
a relevant answer to the
question that was asked. Up
here, you can see that context
relevance, the average context relevance
score is 0.8. For the two
pieces of context that were retrieved, Both of
them individually got scores
of 0.8. We can
see the chain of
thought reason for why
the LLM evaluation
gave a score of 0.8
to this particular response from
the RAG in the retrieval step. And
then down here,
you can see
the groundedness evaluations. So this was
one of the clauses
in the final answer. It got a score
of one. And over here is the
reason for that score. You
can see this was the
statement sentence,
and the supporting evidence backs it
up. And so
it got a full score
of one on a
scale of 0 to 1,
or a full score
of 10 on a scale of zero to 10.
So previously, the kind
of reasoning and information
we were talking about through slides
and in the notebook,
now you can see
that quite neatly in
this StreamLit local app that runs on
your machine. You
can also get a detailed
view of the timeline, as well
as get access to the full
JSON object. Now let's
look at an example where
the rag did not
do so well. So
as I look
through the evaluations, I
see this row with a low groundedness score
of 0.5. So let's click on that. That
brings up this example. The question
is how can altruism be beneficial in
building a
career? There's a response.
If I scroll down
to the groundedness evaluation,
then both of the sentences in the final
response have low groundedness
score. Let's pick one
of these and look at
why the groundedness score is
low. So you can see
this, the overall response got
broken down into four statements, and the
top two were good, but the
bottom two did not have good supporting
evidence in the retrieved pieces of context.
In particular, if you look
at this last one, the final output
from the LLM says, additionally, practicing
altruism can contribute to personal
fulfillment and a sense
of purpose, which can
enhance motivation and overall well-being,
ultimately benefiting one's career success. While that
might very well be
the case, there was
no supporting evidence found
in the retrieved pieces
of context to ground that statement.
And that's why our
evaluation gives this a low score.
You can play around with
the dashboard and explore
some of these other examples
where the LLM, the final RAG
output, does not do
so well to get
a feeling for the
kinds of failure modes
that are
quite common when you're using RAG applications.
And some of these will get addressed
as
we go into
the sessions on
more advanced RAG techniques, which can
do better in
terms of addressing these failure
modes. Lesson two
is a wrap
with that. In the next lesson, we will
walk through the mechanism
for sentence window-based retrieval
and advanced RAG technique,
and also show you how to
evaluate the advanced technique
leveraging the RAG triad and
true lengths.